<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A comment on the times, or, A character of the enemies of the church. Written by Thomas Wall, Mr. in arts and minister of Jesus Christ.</title>
            <author>Wall, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97024</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W477</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R186183</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45504554</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45504554</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171867</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97024)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171867)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2594:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A comment on the times, or, A character of the enemies of the church. Written by Thomas Wall, Mr. in arts and minister of Jesus Christ.</title>
                  <author>Wall, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 51 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Dulwich College Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171867:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171867:1"/>
            <p>A COMMENT On the TIMES, OR, A CHARACTER Of The Enemies OF THE CHURCH.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Thomas Wall,</hi> Mr in Arts, and Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:171867:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171867:2"/>
            <head>To His Moſt Dear Brother, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>S. VV.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O entitle a Book to the name of a Brother, is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unuſual or undecent; the Primitive Fathers more frequently, in all Ages ſome, no leſs e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent for Piety then Learning, have done it;
<pb facs="tcp:171867:3"/> and it is good to take ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample from thoſe who are capable to give it.</p>
            <p>As well to relieve my own affections, as to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge your kindneſs, I Dedicate this to you: I ſhould have been as little ſatisfied in my ſelf, as ſhown my ſelf thankful to you, had I made any other choice.</p>
            <p>'Tis your acceptance that I crave, and not protection, becauſe it is a diſh not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to all Palats: In
<pb facs="tcp:171867:3"/> Book-feaſts, men hate thoſe that feed on that which themſelves love not. While I would hereby give you a teſtimony of my thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I would not have it prejudicial to its Parent: I hope the Author you may own, though not the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. Much of my ſupport have I received from you, and (to ſpeak in my ſecond Religion, gratitude) though I ſhould pay all I have, I ſhould have all to pay: Tis yet my comfort<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as God
<pb facs="tcp:171867:4"/> hath made you a means of doing good to me, ſo he hath he made me an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to embalm your name. To which I will add one grain more, my Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: Beſeeching God to bleſs you with the ſame bleſſings which I beg for the perſon of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Brother, Thomas Wall.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:171867:4"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF thou art a part of the Subject of this Diſcourſe, thy reduction into the Boſom of the Church is my aim therein; and ſurely my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires thereunto are very ſtrong, but can ſend no help to my endeavors. Arguments can never prevail, where we are reſolved to perſiſt. Many men (even with diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage)
<pb facs="tcp:171867:5"/> fight with death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they think they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver truly conquered, who had rather die, then be ſo; and ſo make a fooliſh Bargain with the world, exchanging their lives for reputation. And ſo many perſiſt in deſtructive errours, ſillily thinking they are never overcome, while themſelves do not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it, and loſe the Truth, to ſave credit: Where then just arguments cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, there is no hopes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim. He, to whom man
<pb facs="tcp:171867:5"/> never ſpake the like, ſpake yet to no purpoſe to ſuch men, but yet he ſpake: So holy a preſident ſecures my at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt: If thou therefore wilt not permit me to benefit thy ſoul, at leaſt give me leave to diſcharge my own. But if thou art a Reader, who haſt as well courage to own the truth, as knowledge to diſcern it, let not thy affections to read, out-run thy judgement in the reading, fully to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the dependence of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſentence with the former,
<pb facs="tcp:171867:6"/> may haply require more then perfunctory peruſal; the want of a more ſevere obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance may be injurious to thy ſelf, as well as to me, it may be a loſs to both. I have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed my name hereunto, not that I ſuppoſe ſo mean a piece can gain any reputation to my name, or my name to it, but that my holy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Mother may take notice ſhe hath one Son the more, who hath a greater zeal to ſerve her, then ability; who had rather diſcover his weakneſs, then
<pb facs="tcp:171867:6"/> neglect his duty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If any deſire to have a further account of me, I am content to give them this convenient notice, That as there is no tittle in this Treatiſe either directed or intended againſt this preſent <hi>Government,</hi> ſo do I profeſs my ſelf willing to yeild all ſubmiſſive obedience to it. Among other Arguments wherewith I have ſatisfied my Conſcience for ſo doing, this is one, <hi>For that I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it was by a ſpecial Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine providence raiſed up,
<pb facs="tcp:171867:7"/> to give a ſtop to the violent and unrighteous actions of theſe men, who now by an argument taken out of their own mouths, muſt be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to confeſs, That either the deſigne at which they drove, was wicked, or themſelves wicked in the managing of it.</hi> In what I have writ, it is little to me to be judged by men, it is God that judgeth the heart. I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect not ſucceſs herein from popular noiſes, but the ſecret bleſſing of the ſame righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:171867:7"/> God, who knows the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of a heart inflam'd with zeal to his glory, and the Churches peace: And if I reclaim none that are fallen, I have my hire, if I can but confirm them that ſtand.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:171867:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171867:8"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſalm 68. 30.</bibl>
               <q>Rebuke, O Lord, the company of the Spear-men (or the beaſt of the reeds) the multitude of the Bulls, with the Calves of the people; till they ſubmit themſelves with pieces of ſilver<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the men that delight in war.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>LEt God ariſe, and let his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies be ſcattered;</hi> ſo begins this Pſalm, and it ſhall be the ſubject of my diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>When the enemies of God riſe up againſt his Church, it is time for the Church to fall down to God, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore his aid againſt thoſe enemies. Holy <hi>Prayers</hi> are more powerful then profane <hi>Swords:</hi> It is not ſo much the arm that imploys them, as the cauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which they are employed, that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171867:9"/> makes the ſwords profane. The vigour of faith in humble devotions, hath a greater prevalency, then the valour of the arm in an abuſed inſtrument of cruelty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Samuel</hi> wrought no leſs deliverance for Iſrael, then <hi>Gideon</hi> or <hi>Sampſon;</hi> and yet I never find him in the head of their Troops, The people fought, but it was he obtained the victory. In vain is that Religion, whoſe Patron cannot ſhield its Profeſſors: In vain are any attempts againſt it, if he can. It is good ſeeking help from an all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powerful hand. If the Bulls roar for rage againſt the Church, it is time for the Lambs to bleat out for reſcue. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke, O Lord, the company,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>A ſecret ordination ſummons all things to the end of their being, the glory of God. The very malice of his enemies ſhall ſet forth the try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of his mercy and power, in the preſervation of his Church. <hi>It may
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:171867:9"/> be ſtrongly oppoſed, but not wholly ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What can the Church do againſt ſo many adverſaries, and ſo violent? The leſs help it finds on earth, the more it ſeeks from heaven. The more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent are her adverſaries, the more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt are her prayers. <hi>Rebuke, O Lord, the company,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The words contain, Firſt, A Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of God's enemies. Secondly, An Imprecation againſt thoſe ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>The enemies are marſhalled into four ranks.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A company of Spear-men, or (as ſome Tranſlations read it) the Beaſt of the reeds.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The multitude of the Bulls.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The calves of the people.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The men that delight in war.</p>
            <p>The Imprecation is alſo two-fold; The firſt more gentle; it is but <hi>Rebuke the Spear-men;</hi> and that with a limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:171867:10"/> too; <hi>till they ſubmit themſelves with pieces of ſilver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For they that will not, but delight in war, more ſeverely deal with ſuch, <hi>Scatter them; Scatter the men that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in war.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I enter upon the deſcription of theſe enemies of the Church, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their ſeveral ranks, obſerve firſt from the general ſcope of the Text,</p>
            <p>That the Church of God never wanted enemies, never will. <hi>There is no peace to the wicked,</hi> ſaith God: There ſhall be no peace to the godly, ſay the wicked. The wicked ſhall have no peace which God can give; the godly ſhall have no peace which the wicked can take away.</p>
            <p>God is the Lord of all the earth, it is fit that all parts of the earth ſhould yeild him ſome tribute of ſouls. There may be ſeven thouſand and one in one part of the earth; but alas, what is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171867:10"/> ſeven thouſand and one in one part, to ſcarce one of ſeven thouſand in all the other parts: Sure I am, God's flock is but a little one; all the reſt are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Whoever are the enemies, great is their enmity; and proportionable thereunto, their cruelty.</p>
            <p>Whoever are the enemies: for there are enemies without the pale of the Church, and there are ſome within. Some without. There are, that hate the Church, the ſeed of the Serpent, their father's own brood: <hi>Ye are of your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the divel,</hi> ſaith our Saviour Chriſt. There are, that mock it; an Iſhmaeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh iſſue: There are, that deride, <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballets</hi> progeny. There are, that rail at it, <hi>Rabſhekah</hi>'s race. There are, that curſe it, <hi>Balaams</hi> brood; All ſeek to deſtroy it.</p>
            <p>There is no agreement between good and evil: Neither of which can ſubſiſt in any part of the other: Meet they may, but not unite: There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171867:11"/> good which is not wholly ſo. The leaſt defect changeth the title. Thus ſtands it alſo between truth and falſhood: Truth is but one, it hath no ſubſiſtence but in it ſelf admits of no agreement with what is not one with it. Look then what difference there is in the nature of the things which are entertained; ſuch difference there is in the affections of thoſe that do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs them.</p>
            <p>Religion is the ſureſt tye of love: where this knits not the hearts, there can be no perfect Union. A ſeeming truce there may be, but no true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord. It is their Religion (true or falſe) which all Nations of the world believe themſelves moſt engaged, both to defend and propagate. When this comes into competition, that ſpurious concord which is knit by ſecular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, like ſome goodly Fabrick founded upon the ſands, is ſuddenly overthrown with every puff of paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:171867:11"/> or miſpriſion. Enmity grounded on difference of Religion, may be lull'd aſleep by ſome ſecular intereſts, but cannot be extinguiſhed: If the cradle be not continually rocked, it quickly wakes; like a fire which hath ſome while lay ſmothering under the pile, breaks forth ere long more violently into a ſudden flame.</p>
            <p>If diſagreement in m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tters of faith cauſeth enmity, the more contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one faith is to another, the greater is that enmity. The world ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced three, and but three ſeveral Religions; the Jewiſh, Chriſtian, and Mahumetan. The Jews expect their Meſſiah yet to come, who with great ſtate and glory, ſhall ſubdue all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to his Scepter, and reigne glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly with them upon the earth.</p>
            <p>The Mahumetans have their Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our already come; and ſhall come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and receive them into a paradice above, to all fleſhly delights: Wine,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171867:12"/> and Women, Muſick, Banquettings, and all things that delight a ſenſual and brutiſh appetite.</p>
            <p>Neither of theſe are ſo contrary the one to the other, as the Chriſtian is to both; teaching againſt the one, that the Saviour of the world is already come; whoſe Palace was a Stable, and his Couch a Manger; whoſe Crown was Thorns, and his Scepter a Croſs; whoſe Revenews was poverty, and his State humility; whoſe Sword was his Word, and his conqueſt Dying. In a word, whoſe Kingdom was not of this world.</p>
            <p>Teaching againſt the other, nothing but ſpiritual joys, and incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible conſolations in the glorious viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and fruition of God.</p>
            <p>Go to now, O thou Chriſtian, go to the Jews firſt, and tell them, You are a faithleſs Nation; your Meſſiah is come, and ye have rejected him, and with cruel hands have crucified
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:171867:12"/> the Lord of life; and therefore your expected felicity is turned to miſery<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>your glorious reign over all Nations, to a no leſs ſtrange, then ſad diſſipati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over all the earth; and your car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſecurity, to ſpiritual confuſion: Wilt thou tell them this, and not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect their enmity?</p>
            <p>From the Jew, go to the Turk, and tell him, abuſed Muſſelman, your Prophet is an Impoſtor, his law, a lye, the carnal delights which he has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed you, will turn to unutterable dolours of ſoul, his beautiful women into miſhapen hags, your harmonious muſick, into hideous howling; and your delicious fare, into ſurfe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of wo and bitterneſs. Wilt thou tell him this, and not expect his enmity?</p>
            <p n="2">2. But ſecondly, There are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies within the pale of the Church too: <hi>It is not</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) an open e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy that hath done me this diſhonour, for then I could have born it: But it is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171867:13"/> thou, mine own familiar, we walked in the houſe of God as friends,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>A ſtab from a friend, wounds the heart deeper then the body: while the body weeps in blood at the ſtroke, the ſoul bleeds in tears at the unkindneſs: <hi>Brutus</hi> received a greater wound from <hi>Caeſar</hi> then he gave, and <hi>Caeſar</hi> a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er wound from <hi>Brutus</hi> then his wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, when he cryed, <hi>&amp; tu fili Brute!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That misfortune doth moſt amaze, which we do leaſt expect; and thoſe injuries do moſt trouble, which we leaſt deſerve. No ſight ſo uncouth, as to ſee children pierce thoſe Breaſts which gave them ſuck. Good milk turns to bad blood in a wicked heart. The juice of the ſame Flower which becomes honey in the Bee, converts to poyſon in the Spider. Corrupt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections abuſe the greateſt bleſſings.</p>
            <p>O dear and ſacred Mother! My ſoul ſhall weep in ſecret for thy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful ſons: theſe Birds had not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:171867:13"/> peck'd out thine eyes, hadſt not thou brought them out; nor kick'd againſt thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hadſt not thou fed them full of ſuch excellent viands of knowledge, which thus puffs them up. Haſt thou purchaſt ſuch a pure Reformation for them, from that adulterous Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of Rome, with ſo much blood of thy deareſt children, that they ſhould turn their weapons into thine own bowels, to ſeek for a new one there?</p>
            <p>There are ſure ſome crudities in their ill-diſpoſed ſtomacks, that have turned the wholſom food of the Church into theſe venomous practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: My Meditations have ſuggeſted four.</p>
            <p>1. Scrupuloſity. 2. Envie. 3. Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. 4. Ambition or Pride. Upon which, theſe four Beaſts in the Text do act their enmity againſt the Church: Scrupuloſity ſets forth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us the Beaſt of the reeds: Envie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:171867:14"/> Bulls: Ignorance the Calves, and Pride the men that delight in war.</p>
            <p>Scruples are the reeds: the Beaſt that lurks in them, is a peeviſh ſpirit: which thence takes all occaſions to prey upon the peace of the Church. Every blaſt of wind ſhakes the bend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reed to and fro: every idle ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſtaggers the unſetled humoriſt in his obedience. Were theſe doubts the zeal of a well meaning mind, there might be place for pity, though not excuſe. Ignorance hath no praiſe, but what it gains by yeilding. There is ſafety in the greater and leſs degree of knowledge, whiles the middle ſort lies open to all aſſaults. The greater doth ſurmount all captious apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: the leſs, out of conſcience of its own weakneſs, ſubmits to the gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of more able judgements: while the middle degree finds force enough to lead them into many labyrinths of doubts, but none to conduct them out.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:171867:14"/>
            <p>But if their hearts be not as faulty as their heads, there is the ſpirit of meekneſs to reſtore, whom the ſpirit of errour hath miſled. 'Tis the Beaſts in the reeds that marreth all. A peeviſh ſpirit in a ſcrupulous conſcience. When love of contention would ſeem deſire of aſſurance, every ſtraw ſeems a block<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> How many fooliſh doubts are propoſed, wherein nothing is diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, but the weakneſs of him that raiſed them. A weak brain, and a wilful heart, commonly go hand in hand: The one begins the quarrel, and the other maintains it. To endeavour their conviction, in ſtead of quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fire, does but blow the coals: Where ſatisfaction is but pretended to, it is never received; or if haply<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> really intended, yet if not received, ſuſpition is but augmented; in either caſe, further diſpute doth more exaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate then reclaim. They fear in ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing nothing but preſent contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:171867:15"/> which though they cannot ſcape, they will not acknowledge; and though they cannot divert con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, as uſually they do, by ſtarting to ſome other matter, if they cannot (I ſay) divert conviction, they yet will ſmother it in an outbraving contempt: A perverſe generation, which will not open their eyes to ſee a truth, which either they do not know, or not affect: Nothing can ſilence them, but either their own confuſion, or elſe the Churches. And this is the firſt, <hi>the beast of the Reeds;</hi> a peeviſh ſpirit in a ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous conſcience.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is Envie, herein fitly emblematized by the Bull; for who can ſtop an enraged Bull? And who can ſtand before envie? ſaith the wiſe man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 27. Nothing is either more miſchievous or laſting, then enmity, whoſe foundation is laid upon envie.</p>
            <p>Firſt, where envie is, there is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and every evil work, ſaith St.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171867:15"/> 
               <hi>James.</hi> It is impoſſible they ſhould be good themſelves, that maligne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for being ſo: or, that grieve, not becauſe themſelves want, but that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other hath: Not becauſe themſelves are evil, but becauſe another will not be ſo too: Miſchief muſt needs be their greateſt delight, whoſe greateſt grief is anothers good,</p>
            <p>Neither is it more hateful for its ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, then for its continuance. An injury may be forgotten, where ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance makes not the offenders more inſolent. But envie never ceaſeth, becauſe that ceaſeth not which occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons it. Will you ſee one of theſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Bulls? You ſhall find <hi>Zedekiah</hi> with his iron horns, bellowing out de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance againſt <hi>Micaiah,</hi> in the voice of exprobation: <hi>Which way went the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord from me to thee?</hi> How hath innocence and deſert been batted by the ſalvage Bulls of theſe times? Goring the ſides of their reputation
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:171867:16"/> with the horns of miſpriſion and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction: And like that elder brother of theirs, the fore-named <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> blaſpheming the Spirit of the Lord, by aſcribing thereunto the acts of that ſpirit, that luſteth unto envie. But more of theſe in the proper place. Let this ſuffice for the ſecond ground of their enmity.</p>
            <p>The third is ignorance, diſcovering its ſelf in the Calves of the people. Calves you know are but <hi>ſtollida ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malia,</hi> ſilly creatures, do but follow where their Sires do lead them. Thoſe Calves of the Jewiſh Nation, had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver cryed up the Lord Jeſus to be cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified for a ſeducer, had not themſelvs been ſeduced by thoſe envious Bulls, the chief Prieſts and Scribes, who perſwaded the people to ask <hi>Barabbas,</hi> and crucifie Jeſus. <hi>I wiſt now (Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) that thorow ignorance ye did it, or elſe you would not have crucified the Lord of life,</hi> ſaith St <hi>Peter.</hi> Ignorance
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:171867:16"/> is the mother of all miſchief, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be that leads it, miſerable are the effects thereof.</p>
            <p>Somtimes it is lead by paſſion, which overſways the judgement. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doth more unman us, then this vice: a violent paſſion of grief at the proſperity of the wicked, tranſported even <hi>David</hi> himſelf, almoſt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the generation of God's ſaints: his own teſtimony ſhall be our war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant; <hi>So fooliſh was I, and ignorant, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as a beaſt before thee.</hi> Another fit of furious zeal (for zeal is but a paſſion, if it be not according unto knowledg) enflamed Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to a bloody per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of God's Church.</p>
            <p>Somtimes it is lead by affection, which blinds the judgement. Great affection is ſubject to great deceit: It firſt believes a poſſibility of that, to the liking whereof it is enchained: then ſtrains the wit to find out argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to prove it as poſſible, as pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:171867:17"/> The poſſibility of it thus fancied, begets a conceit that eaſily clothes it ſelf in a contented errour.</p>
            <p>Somtimes ignorance is lead by ſelf conceit, which ſeduceth the judgment. The conceit of knowledge, ruines al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as many as the profeſſed want of it: How many had been better taught, if they had not thought they needed it not? How many had been happy, if they had had more knowledge, and leſs opinion of it? <hi>Knowledge puffeth up,</hi> ſaith St <hi>Paul,</hi> but that the conceit of it only ſhould do ſo too, is not more lamentable then uſual. Buſie ignorance is ever accompanied with an opinion of wiſdom.</p>
            <p>Nor do ſuch more offend in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion they have of themſelves, then in that they have of others: They have a bad opinion of all that flatter not that good one they have of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: Corrupt minds hate thoſe that love not that which they like in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:171867:17"/> This is another ground of that enmity that ſprings from ignorance. Let's ſee a fourth.</p>
            <p>Somtimes it is lead by a prepoſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which prevents the judgement: There is nothing more dangerous, then an haſty admittance of any thing into our allowance: What hath once won conſent upon the Will, is hardly removed. Deliberation preſuppoſeth doubt, and tends to choice; where choice is made, and we are already reſolved, deliberation is excluded as needleſs; and the errour is both ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and digeſted, ere the truth is propoſed; and when it is, it is reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: for prepoſſeſſion begets affection, affection is impatient of contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: where we love to retain, we love not thoſe which would diſſwade us from it, that's another.</p>
            <p>Somtimes it is lead by ſelf-intereſt, and that corrupts the judgement. If godlineſs be great gain, as St <hi>Peter</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:171867:18"/> ſaith, what are they that make great gain out of their godlineſs? A man may poſſibly reap ſecular advantage by that ſervice which he does for God: but not greedily affect it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the juſt cenſure of guilt. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> would not be made rich by the King of <hi>Sodom.</hi> Either greedily or unjuſtly to heap up profit to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the proſecution of God's ſervice, is an undoubted argument that it was their own benefit, and not God's glory, that gave firſt motion to thoſe endeavours; although the deſire of gain may ſo blind the eyes, and pervert the judgement, as to deem the ſervice will acquit the guilt of thoſe corrupt affections. <hi>Saul</hi> had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver impleaded the intent of ſacrifice in the reſervation of the Amalekitiſh cattel, had it not yeilded him ſome hope to wipe off the guilt of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience thereby. And although I dare not affirm, yet I dare ſuppoſe, that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:171867:18"/> his words did but ſpeak his thoughts, and yet thoſe thoughts gave no dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution to his ſin, becauſe it was an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil eye firſt conveyed the motion of that ſervice into his heart.</p>
            <p>When men make ſelf-intereſt the ſphere of their actions, they neither ſee, nor underſtand beyond it. And therefore St <hi>Paul</hi> made ſelf-ſeeking one character of the Churches ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: <hi>All ſeek their own.</hi> The primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians did juſtly glory in the community of theſe outward things, as one evidence of their integrity. If this community did firſt help to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the Church, for ought I know (ſo far as it pleaſeth God to permit) ſelf intereſt may help to pull it down. Theſe are the five grounds of that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity which ſprings from ignorance.</p>
            <p>The fourth general ground is pride, which ſets forth the men that delight in war. The analogie holds in this: Other ſins hate the light, Pride only
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:171867:19"/> loves to be ſeen: The commiſſion of other ſins is attended with ſhame, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps we are humbled for them too, Pride only delights and glories in it ſelf; as therefore pride delights in its own enormity, ſo do they that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in war, glory in their cruelty: ſober minded men wage war out of neceſſity, and have peace for their end, blood-thirſty and deceitful men raiſe war for delight, and have tyrannie for their aim. It is a prodigious pride in the hearts of theſe men in the valuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of themſelves, that think the blood of others a price low enough for their ambitious ends: But all may not aſpire: there is alſo a ſpiritual pride, which as it is more epidemical, ſo is it more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to men and Religion: Both the knowing are infected with it, and the ignorant too: It befools both, and by a ſtrange kind of working, it makes the knowing more learnedly ignorant, and the ignorant more opiniately
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:171867:19"/> knowing; In both, it works a delight to diſturb the peace of the Church.</p>
            <p>In reference to the firſt: There is nothing more dangerous then know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge without grace, humility, and charity. The greateſt hereſies have ſprung from the deepeſt wits. <hi>Thy wiſdom and thy knowledge have pervert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee,</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> Knowledge is good, without which the mind is not good, ſaith <hi>Solomon:</hi> but it oft proves bad, becauſe they are bad who uſe it. Thoſe reaches of the brain, which tend not to unity, are the buds of fury, not diſcretion; and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue more a love of contention, then deſire of Reformation; whether it be in oppoſing eſtabliſhed truths, by ſtraining the wit to find out how rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon might back their diſ-affection to them, or elſe, by forging of errours, by caſting a fraudulent ſhew of reaſon upon thoſe things which are indeed reaſonleſs: Either way yeilding an
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:171867:20"/> equal glory, ſtirs them up to ſhew the bravery of their buſie ſpirits. And there is no ignorance ſo miſchievous as perverted knowledge; nor doth Pride work only upon the knowing, but upon the ignorant alſo: Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by arrogating a conceit of thoſe abilities, which as far tranſcend their capacities, as their conceit tranſcends their abilities. The men are in a dream, conceit is no more, but that's enough to beget a faculty <hi>ſuperſentiendi;</hi> by vertue whereof they are able to teach their teachers: if theſe were as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to learn, as they were to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct. Somtime again, by condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all they cannot underſtand; and contemning learning, becauſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves want it: as if (as that Oracle of humane wiſdom did once obſerve) reaſon were the only enemy of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and childiſh ſimplicity the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ghoſtly wiſdom. Thus doth their practiſe juſtifie the wiſe man's
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:171867:20"/> conſtant aſſeveration, by pride only cometh contention.</p>
            <p>Thus have I ſhown you that the Church hath enemies both abroa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and at home; and the grounds of that enmity: A word of their cruelty, and then I will ſhew you what Beaſts they be.</p>
            <p>We can as little expect, as find mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy at the hands of the profeſſed ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Church: Their Religion doth as much commend, as their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination excite their cruelty: But that the waters of the Sanctuary ſhould be turned into blood, is the aſtoniſhment of Angels as well as men. Oh that the blood of the Covenant God made with men, ſhould be turned into a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of blood, the engagement of Chriſtians to devour one another! A Turkiſh cruelty befits them, who have practically tranſlated Chriſt's Goſpel into <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s Alcoran.</p>
            <p>Nor does the retained name of, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:171867:21"/> profeſſion of Chriſtianity, ſerve to any other end, then that by ſeeming religious, they may be more ſecurely malicious. Agreements in ſome points, does but heighten the hatred occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by difference in others: Falſe zeal tranſports them, fury knows no mean; doth neither fear, nor is ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with revenge. Like as we ſee in ſome ſudden tumults, where there is ſtore of pates, there is ſtore of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion; in which, while any one breaks forth into outrage and miſchief, emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and deſire to ſeem no leſs zeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then he, prompts the ſecond to act the like, or a greater miſchief, till ſome few hands hath conveyed the example to all. So likely, when difference of opinion cauſeth difference of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it breaks forth into all hateful ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects; the heart is enflamed with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, that kindles the tongue to all bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter invectives, hateful revilings, terms of reproach, envious detractions, cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:171867:21"/> ſlanders, falſe accuſations. The tongue ſummons up the hands to acts of violence, and haſtneth the feet to ſhed innocent blood, till at length all the affections joyn in the conſpiracy, and help to ſet forward the miſchief: love to their errors doth excite them, hope to prevail doth encourage them, paſſion precipitates them, and fear ſuggeſts neceſſity upon them, to go on, where nothing but ruine is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected in deſiſting: for that Religion being a matter of higheſt concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the undiſpenſable prop of States, the oppoſers thereof expect no favour, if ſucceſs in the defence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of prove anſwerable to the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours; and it is uſual to ſhew no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, where we expect none; much leſs to expect any, where we have ſhewed none; they muſt be cruel.</p>
            <p>Thus far of the propoſition raiſed from the general ſcope of the Text. I muſt now produce the enemies them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:171867:22"/> and will firſt draw them up, and ſhew them in a full body, and then ſet them in their ſeveral ſtations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Beaſt of the Reeds are a certain ſort of people, that undermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the peace of the Church by a fained ſhew of holineſs, theſe heap up Teachers to themſelves, who make a breach in the quiet ſtate thereof, and are the Bulls of the Text: who by bellowing out reviling reproaches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the eccleſiaſtical policy, beget the Calves of the people, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſedly run to their aſſiſtance, who ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving at the very point of bringing their long endeavours to a wiſhed pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod, up ſtarts a fourth ſort, the men of the Text that delight in war, I mean, this ſpiritual warfare, in whom alone (thanks be to ſome Romiſh Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites for it) the art and policy of the other three do joyntly meet: As firſt, pretending as great, nay, greater ſhew of holineſs. 2. Arrogating bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:171867:22"/> abilities of teaching by inſpiration, and yet as very Calves as the reſt; and theſe like <hi>Jehu</hi> (though not in act, yet in deſire) march furiouſly on, beat down all before them, ſnatch the power out of the others hands, beat down Churches, diſanuls all Orders, overthrows all Eccleſiaſtical policy, confounds Religion, and delight in it too, and glories in their miſchief. Thus have I ſhown the enemies in groſs, obſerve them now in their particular ranks.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Beaſt of the Reeds, ſome tranſlations read, a company of Spear men; the word in the Original re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciles the reading: It ſignifies both a company, and a Beaſt, ſay Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors upon the text. If we tranſlate it a company, it imports a rank of men, armed with Spears, made of a certain kind of Reeds: Spears were in uſe in <hi>David</hi>'s time, they uſed then that wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon to gore the ſides of his myſtical
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:171867:23"/> body, with which a wretched caitiff pierced the ſide of his natural body, <hi>John</hi> 19. 34. But if we refer the ſenſe to the ſignification of a Beaſt, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes ſome perillous beaſt, which out of the covert of their reedy thickets, attends the opportunity of their deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red prey, the ſpecification of theſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Beaſts in the text, prompts my inclination to this ſenſe. What man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Beaſt this ſhould be, my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer reading determines not; Our Chriſtian <hi>Seneca</hi> out of <hi>Caſſiodor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> conjectures it a Lyon, <hi>Leones canneta reliquerunt,</hi> ſaith he. Give me leave to add <hi>Pardus</hi> unto <hi>Leo;</hi> If <hi>Leones,</hi> Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for their proud inſulting; <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardi,</hi> Leopards, for their cunning inſinuating. The great Naturaliſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves it of this beaſt, the Leopard, that being by nature endowed with a ſweet odoriferous ſcent, but of a formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſpect, will hide it ſelf in ſome ſecret place (what better then a thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:171867:23"/> of reeds?) for otherwiſe, the ug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of its ſhape would more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright, then the ſweetneſs of its ſcent allure: the terror of its ſight being thus ſecured, his ſweet ſavour and ſcent allures other Beaſts to the place, upon whom, when they come within the compaſs of his reach, he ſeizeth thence upon, as his deſired prey.</p>
            <p>Your thoughts cannot fall beſides the application. The Hypocrite is this Beaſt. A generation of ſuch beaſts have made this age infamous to all poſterity, who cloak their miſchievous intent under a ſhew of ſanctity. Holy ſemblances, religious proteſtations, pretences of Reformation, are the ſweet allurements, whereby they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract the hearts, and ſteal the affections of the ſilly Calves; whom, when the pleaſing ſavour of theſe Saint-like profeſſions, have drawn into an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement with them, they make the inſtruments of their own thraldome,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:171867:24"/> and the Churches ruine. As the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel did of old, ſo ſtill his ungodly imps, betray others to the guilt of evil practiſes, by faming ſome good to be reaped by it. There be many ſecret reaches in the myſtery of iniquity; they pretend good, when they act e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil; and intend evil, when they act good. Crafty and ſubtle men ſeem al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways good, that they may be once bad to purpoſe. All operations tend to ſome end: It was an aim at an higher degree of perfection, that firſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned ſin in the world; and the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt evils are ſtill occaſioned by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending it.</p>
            <p>When men appear ſo good, and are not, they muſt have ſome evil end, or elſe ſome ill intent: The firſt thing they conceive withal, is glory and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe: Who take upon them the ſemblance of doing like Saints, but are not, although they ſtand condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of themſelves; becauſe they know
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:171867:24"/> how to be good, and are not: yet men uſually dare not think them to be bad, whom they ſee know ſo well how to be good. Glittering pretences dazles the eyes of men, God only judges of the action by the heart, man of the heart by the actions. When as there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God hath placed majeſty as well as beauty in the face of Vertue, that where the one cannot allure, the other may enforce reſpect: Hence it is, that wicked men admire and reverence that power of godlineſs, which yet they deny to practiſe; and vain-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious men practiſe that godlineſs, the power whereof they yet deny: covet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more to be honoured for it, then bettered by it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So glory is the firſt.</p>
            <p>Self-intereſt is the ſecond. Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous they will be, and't be but for the benefit they receive thereby. <hi>Saul</hi> will be devout, that he may preſerve ſuch goodly cattel; he will keep them to ſacrifice to the Lord: ſome perhaps to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:171867:25"/> God, but moſt to his belly. The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Sichem</hi>'s country will enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the covenant of God with Iſrael, on condition that Iſrael's ſubſtance might be theirs, <hi>Gen.</hi> 34. 23. It is the hateful practiſe of theſe times, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the encreaſe of knowledge hath been the bane of practiſe, to pretend Religion, and intend Promotion: But God and Mammon cannot dwell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Religion was never the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal end of thoſe undertakings, where they that manage the cauſe, thrive ſo faſt upon it, and grow more rich, then they were before devout. A rich man may be truly pious, but they are juſtly ſuſpected, who ſo greedily work rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es out of piety: the bleſſing is promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to them that loſe all for Chriſt, not to them who gain all by him. It is very hard for a rich man to enter into the Kingdom of heaven, but it is hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for them that make themſelves rich by pretending to it. They can expect
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:171867:25"/> no reward from God, that pay them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo well for the ſervice they do for him. Self-intereſt then, is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond end.</p>
            <p>But thirdly, Will you ſee the very Divel in <hi>Samuel</hi>'s Mantle? Here comes malice and miſchief under the cloak of piety too. How often hath malice wrought out its own ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wherein the pretence hath been on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly zeal to Religion? How often have men, by how much the more they have pretended ſervice to God, by ſo much the more injurious violence have they harboured under that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, to proſecute their diſſenting Brethren? They that dare rob God of glory, leſs care what outrage and miſchief they do to man, ſo they may do it with credit, advantage, and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And although to a more vigilant obſervation, hypocriſie is ſeldom without thoſe practiſes, without which we ſhould not know it to be hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:171867:26"/> God permits them to go ſo far, that till by their fruits they might be known, yet vulgar eyes ſees not the malice and miſchief that is palliated under ſuch ſpecious and plauſible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuations. I had almoſt ſaid, that miſchief is ever intended by ſpecious pretences, which are ever aſſumed for the effecting of it. And the gall of this bitterneſs is, that this miſchief is not to be diverted, either by lenity, or benefits, or by wiſdom: Firſt, not by lenity; for if they think they do well, (as many of the ſeduced Calves may do, like thoſe in Jeruſalem, <hi>who fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Abſolon in the ſimplicity of their hearts</hi>) upon this account, they think toleration of them, to be an effect of that awful regard which is due unto ſuch pretenſions, and not of lenity: which gives more encouragement to proceed, then works any relenting ſubmiſſion. Or if the ſpirits either of malice, or of contention, or of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:171867:26"/> world employ them, as without doubt one of theſe ſpirits does the Bulls of the Text, forbearance then does but ſerve for an incitement more contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuouſly to provoke. Secondly, The miſchief is not to be diverted by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits; ſor that advantage is always greater, which they hope to gain by ſucceſsful commotions, then undeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved favour. Laſtly, Not by wiſdom, for ſtrong pretenſions, if they win not belief, yet they make even wiſe men ſuſpend their judgements; if they draw not help, yet they make men that they do not oppoſe. And to be ſure, hypocrites put not off their counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit ſhape, till they have ſo far advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced their intended wickedneſs, till it be paſt redreſs. Nor do they receive diſcouragement from the diſcovery of a few more piercing eyes, for, for the moſt part, men are generally ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enſnared by it, or elſe amated; either engaged to help, or reſolved not
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:171867:27"/> to oppoſe; and who are back'd with the aſſiſtance of many, fear not the power of a few. In a word, there is nothing more eaſie then to be ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, where men dare make Religion a cloak for their wickedneſs, and dare allow in themſelves, violation of oaths, and the perpetration of any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt and ungodly actions, that may promote their deſigns. And theſe are the firſt rank, the Beaſt of the Reeds. <hi>Rebuke, O Lord, the Beaſt of the Reeds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is a multitude of Bulls. The effects of the rage and brutiſh qualities of theſe beaſts, are found in none more eminently, then in a ſort of factious Miniſters, who creep into the Church of God, and occaſioneth this ſad confuſion of it. <hi>The Pastors are become brutiſh,</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> chap. 10. 21. Brutiſh is a general term, ſet down to expreſs the various effects of their cruel diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are not to be compriſed in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:171867:27"/> any one particular word. Hence it is, that for the waſte they make in the Church, they are called Boars, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80 for their factious Schiſms, Foxes cubs, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2. 15. for devouring ſouls, they ate called ravening Wolves, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 15. for their poyſonſome malice, Serpents, and Vipers, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. for their greedineſs, dogs, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 2. for their bloody perſecution of their Brethren, they are called Bulls of Baſan, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 22. 12. which Pſalm is a Propheſie of Chriſt, the principal actors of whoſe death, were the chief Prieſts and Scribes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to this Beaſt the text reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles theſe their Succeſſors. Bulls, eſpecially if enraged, are fierce, head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong, mad, they roar, ſpurn, ſcrape up earth, traverſe the ground, exalt their horns, breath out fury, and ſcorn all oppoſition whatſoever. Such are the qualities of thoſe factious and ſchiſmatical Miniſters which did infeſt the Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:171867:28"/>
            <p>Firſt, They are fierce: Men of lean abilities, what they cannot attain by deſert, will endeavour by faction; and it is eaſie to find exceptions, when we reſolve to oppoſe: what a nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous iſſue did they pretend burdened their weak and tender conſciences? but all begotten by envie, upon miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apprehenſion; but how weak ſoever their exceptions be, they are violently inſiſted on: What bitter invectives did they froth out againſt a few inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Rites, and things of unimporting conſequence, in compariſon of thoſe many horrid blaſphemies, hereſies, and frenzies, that have hurried ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſand ſouls ſince to hell and damnation? Every fancied diſlike tranſports them into rage and fury; they are all on fire in deteſtation, though the things that incenſe them, carry no other blame, but what their miſconſtruction gives them. <hi>Their hands and their feet ſpeak as loud, as their
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:171867:28"/> tongues,</hi> ſaith the Wiſeman, <hi>Prov.</hi> 6. 13. as if there were as much ſenſe in the noiſe of the one, as in the voice of the other: The leſs reaſon they have for the diſturbance they make, the more would they ſeem to have; they would have the bitterneſs of their malice, evince the betterneſs of their cauſe; and the vehemency of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending, prove them to have ſome great reaſon for the doing that, which indeed ſhews they have neither reaſon nor Religion: An indiſcreet paſſion in all ſtrifes, either imports ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret guilt, or elſe betray us to it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Nor are they more fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious then head-ſtrong. There is no tyrannie like to that of a ſlave, whom vilany hath ſet a cock-horſe: Nothing can divert him from that miſchief which he hath once reſolved; ſo it is in the Iſle of Man. When corrupt affections have inſlaved the judgment, it is to no end for the captive to give a Law
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:171867:29"/> to the Law to the conquerours, which will admit none. When the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are the ſervants to the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour powers of the ſoul, get the maſtery, they commonly beget an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible reſolution not to alter our perſwaſions: Shame will not permit them to yeild, whom deſire of glory cauſed to contend<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The more zeal they have ſhown in a wrong cauſe, the more ignominious would their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction be; and conſequently, their reſolutions more engaged to perſiſt. The Church muſt be pulled down, to make up the breaches of their reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Nothing is more terrible to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious ſpirits, then to read their own ſhame in the ſuppreſſion of miſchief fruitleſly attempted: Reputation muſt maintain what ignorance did broach. To miſ-apprehend, denotes a man. 'Tis head-ſtrong perſiſtance that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grades him into a Beaſt: Sillineſs and ſtubbornneſs fattens them in that Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiality.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:171867:29"/>
            <p>3. In this fury and obſtinacy, they out-run their wits: a violent proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their religionated deſigns of miſchief, tranſports them into ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous fits of madneſs: <hi>The Prophet is a fool, the ſpiritual man is mad,</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Hoſea,</hi> chap. 9. 7. what is folly but a tame madneſs? What is madneſs, but a raging folly? <hi>The fool rageth, ond is confident,</hi> ſaith the wiſe man: mad conceits, mad geſtures, mad practiſes, make up theſe mad Bulls.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Mad conceits; They run to hell, and ſay they are going to heaven: They practiſe the Divel, and ſay they are taught of God ſo to do. They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Religion, and ſay they reſtore it: Sacriledge they would chriſten in blood with the name of devotion; their confuſed and incongruous inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixture of the different parts of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, vain battologies, yea unſavory non-ſenſe, they conceive for method,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:171867:30"/> the direction; for matter, the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate dictates of the holy Spirit; and many ſuch like mad conceits they have.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Mad geſtures; Staring, grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, gnaſhing, toſſing themſelves, this way, that way, up and down; thumping, beating, ſtamping, and the like; theſe they deem the becomming deportments of holy zeal, and divine raviſhment.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Mad actions; Like him who took up a ſtone to beat off a fly from his neighbor's forehead, which knockt out his brains: Or like that other, that to ſhave the hair, cut off the head. I need not ſpeak the application. O once moſt glorious Church, now mended into ruine! O monſtrous Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on! But the proper work of ſuch frantick Bulls, They are mad.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, They are roaring Bulls: With what ſtrained throats do they ſtund the giddy multitude into won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:171867:30"/> and ſeducement? What Civil A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm do they bellow out againſt that Authority, to which the Law of God, and man, and themſelves had ſubject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them? With what impetuous cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours do they blaſpheme God into an engagement with them, by chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging a protection from him, in their ſacrilegious and unjuſt proceedings? As if they would level heaven with hell in the allowance of their practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. With what loud clamours do they cry up the Lord Jeſus into a pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Throne, prepared for him in the F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rge of their own fancies? With what ſwelling words of oſtentation, would they deifie their Cauſe, with a preſumptuous Warrant of its happy ſucceſs? To whom the Proverb hath hapned true, <hi>None more ſhamefully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, then thoſe that thought themſelves moſt confidently aſsured.</hi> Laſtly, How do they thunder out damnation againſt all oppoſers of them? For they are roaring Bulls</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:171867:31"/>
            <p>Fifthly, They ſcrape up earth. No far-fetch'd embleme of theſe ſpiritual Bulls, in their greedy ſcraping up theſe hardned clods of white and red earth. The deſire of wealth and preferment, hath tanght them to be religious. God muſt be beholding to Mammon for the ſervice theſe men do for him. They have prepared Chriſt Jeſus a Throne, but they will be paid well for the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it up. Wicked men hold that Religion beſt, which they moſt thrive by; nor will ſet up any, but by what they may: They had not that prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which they deſired, but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered not they deſired that which they deſerved not; and it is not ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to counterfeit Learning as Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. What? Are they ſo good? and yet ſo covetous? Surely theſe men are the only men that have got a way to reconcile God and the world toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, They exalt their horns:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:171867:31"/> They are as proud as covetous; a pair of ſins that uſually go hand in hand, ſaith pious <hi>Bernard.</hi> There is nothing ſo hateful as a proud Prieſt; becauſe the holieſt Calling makes the greateſt ſinner. Pride was firſt begot in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, by the reflex of an Angel's un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding upon his own excellency, and it ſtill aſpires to an eminency in eminency in them, who profeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves moſt heavenly. Holy ſemblan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces hath ſet upon them an high eſteem in other mens opinions: Self love doubles it in their own. True piety humbles us; It is no marvel if their fained piety puffs them up in a proud eſtimation of themſelves, they deſpiſe others: <hi>Come not near, for I am holier then thou.</hi> With what a ſcornful eye do they look upon thoſe, who have not learn'd an high eſtimation of, and a due ſubmiſſion to them, as the only ſupporters of Religion. Surely Saint <hi>Paul</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>Let every one think
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:171867:32"/> others better then themſelves,</hi> ſpake not to them who make a proud contempt of others, all the arguments they have of their own excellency:</p>
            <p>Seventhly, They breathe out fury: In what bloody characters do they write the evidence of their pride and covetouſneſs? What they cannot at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain by the ſword of God, they will by the ſword of <hi>Gideon:</hi> who ever knew errour not accompanied with violence and cruelty? They ſow Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, raiſe tumults, rend the Church, and run to violence for ſecurity. They more fear the power of men, then of God; or elſe they would never ſeek to ſecure themſelves from the one, by thoſe miſchievous practiſes, which doth more incenſe the other.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Like enraged Bulls, they break thorow all oppoſition; for what can reſtrain them?</p>
            <p>Can perſwaſions? No; for reaſon can never perſwade them to deſiſt,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:171867:32"/> who had no reaſon to attempt, but hope to prevail. They who have no reaſon but their Will, will hear none againſt it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Can Conſcience? No; for they will not fear to commit ſin againſt their Conſcience, who dare to pretend Conſcience for the ſin which they do commit. That Conſcience which will for its own end patronize ſome ſins, to advance thoſe ends will act any.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Can Duty reſtrain them? No; for while they pretend to high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er perfection then is taught in the Church, they forget to acknowledge that degree whereunto ſhe hath brought them; and are more ready to quarrel at her defects, then to reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence her graces, as if thoſe might better juſtifie a ſeparation from her, then theſe challenge any thankfulneſs or duty to her.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Can Laws reſtrain them?
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:171867:33"/> No; for the uſe of Law is not to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, but to enforce: But their Conſcience, they ſay, may not be forced. A true principle, but they may either ignorantly apply it, or elſe maliciouſly: Though the coercive power of the Law hath no juſt domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over the Conſcience, yet may not every ſilly pretence of Conſcience be obtruded, to render the power of Laws of none effect. They ignorantly apply it, who make thoſe things mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Conſcience, upon which the Conſcience has no immediate influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; as certainly it cannot have up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on things which are not directly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited by God's Word. Where o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience is required by lawful Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, wherein yet, a man doubteth whether he may obey or not; that man cannot without ſottiſh ignorance, be ſaid to be perſwaded in Conſcience that he may not obey, unleſs he can produce ſome juſt prohibition from
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:171867:33"/> Scripture, of the things whereunto his obedience is required. Or ſecondly, They may maliciouſly apply it, and often do ſo too, when 'tis the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity that enjoyns them, that doth more diſtaſte, then the things enjoyned. In vain ſhall they complain of ſeverity, that do all they can to provoke it; but in the mean time, whether they apply it ignorantly or maliciouſly, they make no Conſcience to violate thoſe Laws which they pretend would force them againſt their Conſcience.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Can ſhame reſtrain them? No; for the fear of that can never deter them, which they preſume ſhall never happen, eſpecially where there is certain ſhame in deſiſting, and a conceited aſſurance both of gain and glory too in proceeding: Powerful arguments both, to win upon corrupt affections: For ſome will be always found to commend thoſe attempts, that are by never ſo wicked means
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:171867:34"/> crowned with ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Will a perſonal Oath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain them? No; for an Oath, which is a moſt ſacred thing, cannot partake of any thing which is evil, <hi>Herod</hi> ſealed his promiſe with an Oath, but that Oath had no obligation from the ſtrumpets demand. If <hi>Herod</hi> had broke that Oath, it could not have made him perjured; becauſe no Oath can binde to an unlawful action. Whence they may have argued, that they may ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly renounce that obedience, though by oath engaged to it, which an after new light hath diſcovered to be contrary to the power of Godlineſs, but if this new light be nothing el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e but either 1. A ſetled reſolution to do what we have a mind to. Or, 2. Some violent prevailing f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncy, that hath ſtole firſt upon our affections, then upon our judgements. Or 3. A ſtrong per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion begotten by private ends, and received growth from falſe principles.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:171867:34"/> Or 4. Diabolical Infuſion; for it muſt needs be ſo when injurious, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious, and apparent ungodly practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are uſed for the promotion of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended piety; if it be (I ſay) any of theſe pretty Images (which this new light hath inſinuated into theſe men) diſguiſed under the name of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, what ſhall become of them? What will they do? when they ſhall lie under the ſtinging laſhes of a guilty Conſcience, and the either dreadful apprehenſions, or unſufferable ſtrokes of divine wrath and indignation, both for their own breaking through the ſacred tye and band of a juſt, lawful, ancient, ſolemn, and holy oath, and cancelling all other bands of Religion and Reaſon; but alſo, as if men did not run faſt enough to hell and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation before, for that they ſhould hold forth this light to others, to make them run the faſter.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, and laſtly, Will a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:171867:35"/> Covenant reſtrain them? No; for that Covenant which they entered into for ſelf-ends, it failing to effect thoſe ends, they will as readily break, and (if they can) work their deſires in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fruition by any means, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo contrary to that League, or any part thereof: Who fear not to take an oath contrary to God's Law, will not fear to break, if contrary to their own, not ſo much as unlawful, but as invalid: Not, out of conviction that they ought not advance their own ends by it, but out of vexation, that they cannot.</p>
            <p>Thus have I ſhown you the Bulls of the Text. Now let us ſee the Calves of the people, whom they miſlead in their trains of errour. <hi>They cauſe my people to err, by their lightneſs and lies,</hi> ſaith the Prophet. There are no ſuch plagues to a Commonwealth as ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Prieſts. The infection of errour is worſe then the guilt; it no ſooner
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:171867:35"/> finds approbation in one, but it bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows his perſwaſions for entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in another. But keep we to the Bulls, the grand ring-leaders of all; how many pernicious Tenents have found both allowance and entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in vulgar minds, from the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of them, whoſe poſitions they have found to jump with their own affections and private ends, whence proceeds an admiration of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for advantage ſake, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaks, which comes at length to a belief of the infallibility of their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions in all things, whom they finde uncontrollable in ſome, and remark'd for men that pretend to a greater meaſure of ſanctity then others. Now when theſe begin to make a breach in Church, thoſe incitations againſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the preſent ſtate of things, never want favourable audience, which have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared their way by the opinion of their holineſs from whom they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed:
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:171867:36"/> with what ſpungy ſouls do theſe poor Calves ſoak in theſe waters of the Sanctuary, which their applauded Teachers have either ignorantly or deceitfully corrupted, to intoxicate them! They are firſt induced to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, then to defend; and the bold predictions of ſucceſs from the <hi>Zede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiahs</hi> of the times, and a miſchievous confidence in the ſwelling numbers of their partiſans, gives them encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to all acts of violence and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage. Wicked men ask no leave to do, when they find their hearts in their hands; I mean, their power an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to their will: And now tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling with the pangs of a falſe zeal, they fall in labour of a monſtrous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation: Religion, and Liberty of Conſcience, are made the grounds of their quarrel. An eaſie perſwaſion wins the aſſiſtance of the Vulgar to thoſe attempts, whereby they are taught to believe, they ſhall at once do
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:171867:36"/> ſervice to God, and right to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. But hear, O ye ſeduced Calves of the people! It is the ſhew of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that maintains ſin in the world: The world could not be ſo bad as it is, if all that were bad in it did appear ſo. Theſe Bulls could not have train'd you on to theſe acts of violence and outrage, but by diſſembled piety: but you muſt know, it is almoſt as great a crime in matters of Religion, to be deceived, as to deceive. God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire your blood at their hands, but you alſo may die in your ſins; and when you are in hell, it will be no caſe to you that they are more tormented. There is nothing more pleaſing to the Divel, then to ſee his malice againſt the Church, to tryumph in your folly and miſpriſion. It was once piety to build Temples to the publique ſervice of God, and is it now piety to pull them down? Did you pretend to fight for Religion, to keep it from the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:171867:37"/> violation of others, that ye might commit a rape upon it your ſelves? But alas, the wound is incurable; Here is no room for expoſtulation; let us therefore ſee in a word the Religion this many headed monſter hath hatch'd, and the liberty of conſcience they would have: Theſe alſo having their particular aims, either ſecular ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, or deſirous to paſs for men enflamed with a godly zeal, or rather led by both together, for they have learned this art from the Bulls, their Sires, to have reconciled gain and godlineſs, profit and zeal; profit pricks forward zeal, as provender does the Aſs, and their zeal counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanceth them in the profit they get, and then it is piety in them to pull down Churches, which was once pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety to build up: It is pure devotion that conſecrates their fingers to the committing of ſacriledge: It is the fire of zeal that kindles their tongues
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:171867:37"/> to all manner of bitter invectives, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all kind of Order and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; It is love to the truth makes them lovers of themſelves in ſtanding for it: It is hatred of ſin makes them ſo malicious: It is ſeparation from the wicked that makes them void of Chriſtian ſociety, and common Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality; and ſo full of pride, ſcorn, and contempt: It is fear of maintaining idleneſs, that makes them ſo unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table: It is the correction of nature, makes them without natural affection: and the rooting out the wicked, makes them unjuſt: and their liberty of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, is the practiſe of all this impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety permitted with impunity. The ſum of all, It's a Religion that will give them liberty to break down all the Houſes of God in the Land, and ſeize upon the Revenews thereof, and tye the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt to their allowance; a Religion that may give them liberty to commit ſacriledge, to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:171867:38"/> ſpeak evil of Dignities, to turn the wicked out of their eſtates, and inveſt them in their inheritance: Briefly, a Religion that may tolerate and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, yea, and juſtifie them in their covetous, malicious,, cruel, unnatural, uncivil, proud, contemptuous, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable actions. This is only the Religion and Liberty of Conſcience that will pleaſe the Calves: In the ſweet paſtures whereof we will turn them to graſs, and come to the fourth rank, <hi>The men that delight in war.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There be five marks of the delight men take in war.</p>
            <p>Firſt, When they attempt it upon fained cauſes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, upon frivolous cauſes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, When they attempt it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the rules of that faith which they profeſs.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Out of pride and vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious ends.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, The cruelty with which they manage it.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:171867:38"/>
            <p>Anſwerable hereunto, there are five things which in the ſpiritual ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of it, will make up theſe men of blood. Bloody Brains, Bloody Conſciences, a Bloody Religion, Bloody Affections, and laſtly, Bloody hands.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When it attempted upon fained cauſes; There be bloody brain'd men, who are witty in nothing more, then in picking quarrels. It was a wiſe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a wicked King of Iſrael, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding a quarrelſome intent in the Syrian King, in the requeſt of a thing beyond the compaſs of humane pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the cure of <hi>Naamans</hi> leproſie, <hi>Am I in God's ſtead, that he ſhould ſeek occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion againſt me?</hi> The Syrian did not, but the conjecture yet was grounded upon good reaſon. <hi>There is a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, that ſeek rebellion:</hi> that is, do all that they can to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke, that out of enforced juſtice they may ſeek occaſion of revenge: and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:171867:39"/> then like <hi>Jonah,</hi> they dare out-face God and his word, that they <hi>do well to be angry.</hi> They ſeek offences, that they may commit them: and oft times nothing grieves them ſo much, as when they can find no occaſion to be provoked; which when they find not, they fain; if they meet not with, they make: What black comments do they write upon the faireſt actions? All offers of peace they tranſlate into the language of ſuſpition, and meaſures others intents by their own guilt. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s piety in talking to them of peace, is but policy in their gloſs; they had no mind to believe what he ſpake, that had no mind to that of which he ſpake; and the preparations which they make to offend him, they pretend but a neceſſity, to defend themſelves: <hi>While I ſpeak to them of peace, they make themſelves ready to Battel,</hi> ſaith he: but let them ſubtlely inſinuate neceſſary defence, ſure enough the preparations
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:171867:39"/> they make, ſhew a delight in war. Nor are they more crafty in laying the grounds of their hoſtile deſigns, then in managing the proſecution of them. So far as piety may advance them, they can counterfeit innocence, while they oppreſs it. But when it comes to groſs wickedneſs, they can both defie and practiſe it. And this is the firſt thing that make up theſe men of blood; bloody Brains, that plot out occaſions of commotion.</p>
            <p>The ſecond mark is, When they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt it upon frivolous cauſes: Bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Conſciences! Men that out of conſcience can make thoſe quarrels deadly, which indeed deſerve not to be quarrels: Conſciences that can ſwallow down whole draughts of Chriſtian blood, to the effuſion where of a wretched ſcrupuloſity in things of indifferent nature prompted them. Eſtridge Conſciences, that can digeſt iron, but not ſtraw. Conſciences that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:171867:40"/> ſtartle at doing of what God forbideth not, but without remorſe or ſcruple, can fall upon thoſe inhumane practiſes which God abhors; as if a ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous nicety in ſmaller matters, could by way of commutation expiate the guilt of ſuch bloody outrages, which needs muſt damn. Theſe are the ſecond mark.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third mark of the delight they take in war, is, when they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt it contrary to the rules of that faith which they profeſs. Bloody con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences beget a bloody Religion. Chriſt will own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Religion, but what is chriſtned in his own blood; It is the divel's (of whom <hi>Mahomet</hi> learn'd it) that is dipt in the blood of men. Our Saviour came indeed to bring a ſword, but <hi>Peter</hi> muſt not uſe it. Hear O ye Chriſtians! miſtake not your Saviour, meddle not with this ſword. Nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſary it is that offences come, but wo unto them by whom they come.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:171867:40"/> Chriſt came indeed to die, but they were never the leſs wicked that killed him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Can the neceſſity of his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juſtifie that malice, cruelty, and injuſtice by which he ſuffered? God bringeth good out of evil, becauſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe he could not permit it a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the world, without deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it: But doth God allow the evil for the good? Permiſſion is no allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. Or can he make that which is evil in it ſelf to be good? He may not impute a ſin to a man, yet cannot but repute it for a ſin; he may remit the guilt of ſin, but not alter the nature of it: But it ſeems theſe men can do more then God, they can legitimate any wickedneſs, with a <hi>fiat</hi> from the uner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Court of their own Conſciences; for if they cannot, thoſe actions ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which cauſed the death of Chriſt, can never give life to his cauſe. He ſuffered through injuſtice for our fakes, but does he require we ſhould
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:171867:41"/> do it too for his ſake? Oh the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this new light! (for the myſtery of it is as dark as the pit out of which it came) It was once, Thou ſhalt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer wrong of others for his ſake, but now it ſeems we may do it too for his ſake: It was once you ſhall be perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted for my cauſe, but now, we may perſecute: It was once, ye ſhall be killed for my ſake, but now we may kill. Nay, ſo many, the moſt inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, cruel, bloody actions; ſuch, which no generation but this ever did the like; and at which the ears of all poſterity ſhall tingle, have been done, and yet a cauſe we have can make them lawful; a light we have can ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie them: nay more, none truly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned, none zealous for the cauſe of Chriſt, but ſuch who either act, or ſide with the actors of them. But O my ſoul! Come not thou into the ſecrets of this cauſe; and by this light, my better, be not thou directed: For
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:171867:41"/> that cauſe, or that Religion which is planted by ſedition, watered with blood, that brings forth pride, feeds ambition, maintains ſacriledge, nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth hatred, malice, uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and injuſtice, and is upholden by lying, however ſtrength of conceit may ſeduce the judgement, hath no author but ſome of thoſe wicked ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, who have broke looſe from their chains of darkneſs, and transformed themſelves into Angels of light, that they might range a land, to ſeduce the minds, and pervert the ways of a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whoſe hearts, pride, ſelf love, and ſelf conceit had prepared for their entertainment. In a word, 'tis a wicked Religion, eſpecially profeſſing it ſelf Chriſtian, that dares juſtifie proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, contrary to the rules of Chriſt's Goſpel, and they are men of brazen brows, and reprobate ſenſe, that ſhall preſume to divide Chriſt himſelf, as well as his coat; I mean, to enforce
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:171867:42"/> a belief upon us, that he would teach us one thing by his Goſpel, and his Goſpel another thing by them: Or, that that Religion which tolerates the worſt actions, ſhould demonſtrate the beſt Chriſtians: Or, that that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which teacheth us to ſuppreſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious and unjuſt actions, ſhould tolerate the ſame actions, though in its own defence, is a riddle to men and Angels. And thus much of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When they attempt it for proud and vain-glorious ends: Bloody Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. Pride firſt bred the quarrel between God and man. <hi>Adam</hi> would have been a God, before he knew well what it was to be a man; and while he thought to betroth a Deity, he betrayed humanity; and fell, I had almoſt ſaid, as much below himſelf, as he thought to have been above. And there is ſtill a ſecret pride in the heart of man, that lifts up it ſelf to a
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:171867:42"/> ſecet affectation of a Deity: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as a juſt and proper puniſhment, men ſtill as men, aſpire to be what they are not, and reaching in their fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies at an higher degree of perfection in knowledge, they diſquiet both themſelves and others in the purſuit thereof, How did the Arian hereſie fill the whole world with war and blood? If diſcontent firſt broach'd that hereſie, yet it was pride of heart that brewed it, and ſtirred up his buſie ſpirit, by inventing ſome notable no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty of doctrine, to inſinuate to the world, how far his competitor came behind him, who was yet preferred to that Eccleſiaſtical Dignity before him. Of all affections, the deſire of being Authors of ſome new device in matters of Religion, is (if not the ſtrongeſt) yet to ſome moſt pleaſing. There are ſome contentious ſpirits, that hugely delight to ſwim againſt the ſtream. While the thoughts are
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:171867:43"/> tickled with the ſweetneſs of fame, the itch of vain glory preſently infect the powers of the ſoul<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and there is no man which (if that lovely pair, chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and humility interpoſe not) but will dote upon the iſſues of his own brain, and propoſe them to general enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment: yea, they will at once both wonder, and be angry, wonder at the incapacity, and be angry at the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy of any that ſhall refuſe to yeild that approbation and reception of them, which themſelves, the Authors, think them worthy of. Whence ſprings an earneſt deſire (and that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire whets the endeavours, by any means whatſoever, to win entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for them in the allowance and be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>f of men; nor do they regard what practiſes they uſe to effect it. The wickedneſs of the means, is guilded over with the ſplendour of the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation they hope ſhall be gained by it: either fear or favour, inability to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:171867:43"/> or affection to defend, ſtrike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion dumb, and ſomtimes blind, meaſuring juſtice in the cauſe, by the ſword ſhe holds in the one hand, and not by the ballance in the other; but it is not more pleaſing to the Authors, as pernicious to the Church. Like as we ſee in ſecular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts; No man can riſe, but by the fall of another. Every one covets his own advantage, which depending on the deſtruction of anorher, he ſeeks it there. So it is here, Errour can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not riſe, but truth muſt fall; what the one doth gain, the other loſeth; the intereſt of either, depends upon the ruine of the other; and truth and errour never happen to quarrel, but they leave bloody marks behind them upon the body of the Church. But the gall of this bitterneſs too, is, that when the ſucceſs of errour hath crown'd the endeavours of thoſe, whoſe pride of heart and vain-glory
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:171867:44"/> gave it birth; the very fruition of their deſires ſtops not the iſſue: for what is acquired by violence, muſt by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence be preſerved: Hereſie would have leſs guilt, if the defence thereof did not neceſſitate the addition of more, or at leaſt, the continuance of the ſame miſchief, which the intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction gave beginning to: wherein they are not unjuſtly ſaid to delight, if not as the principal end of their deſires yet as a means for the accompliſhment of that end. That's the fourth mark of them that delight in War, attem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted for proud and vain-glorious ends.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The laſt mark is, Their cruelty which they ſhew in managing of it. If there be a bloody heart, there will be a bloody hand too. Men would think it vain to be wicked, if they ſhould not make uſe of their wickedneſs: whoſe covetous and other b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e ends, have carried them beyond the bounds
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:171867:44"/> of Law and Equity, care not whither they run: The apprehenſion of their danger, frights them into all acts of violence, for their ſecurity. They think all plot their ruine, that ſide not with them; and therefore ſeek their own ſafety, though it be with the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of all. But ſafety, which firſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned this cruelty, ends it not. For guilty fear brings malice with it into a wicked heart; when that is eaſed, this will alſo be ſatisfied. So that now diſpoſition cauſeth cruelty, as well as neceſſity, and that ſafety which at firſt was ſought by it, ends at laſt with a delight in it. And thus much of the enemies, I will briefly touch the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precation.</p>
            <p>The Imprecation is made up of two terms, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f different <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffections; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Rebuke</hi> the three firſt; it is <hi>Scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ourth. Whence we note,</p>
            <p>That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt be propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned as well to the manner of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:171867:45"/> as the nature of the offence. Circumſtances, though they do not alter the nature, yet may aggravate the hainouſneſs of crimes. It is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that extends the guilt: and the manner of committing the offence, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhews it capable of being reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in a wholſome rebuke, or elſe worthy of judgement in a juſt diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation. <hi>Rebuke,</hi> and <hi>Scatter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To Rebuke, tends to a poſſible con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, that ends with Reformation. To Scatter, tends to an otherwiſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible fruſtration, that ends with confuſion. Rebuke to amendment, they may ſubmit: Scatter to confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for they delight in miſchief, and it ſhall happen to them. Imprecations are of a dangerous conſequence, they are, I grant, rather to be feared then imitated: yet on the other ſide, I doubt not to affirm, that as our cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to man commands our prayers to God for the converſion of the weak,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:171867:45"/> and ſeduced enemies of the Church; ſo our zeal to the truth and glory of God, may warrant us to pray for the diſſipation of the wilful and malicious enemies thereof. The writings of the Prophets are full of theſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Imprecati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And although St <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> a miracle of underſtanding, ſuppoſes thoſe to be only propheſies of what ſhould come to paſs, then requeſts of what they deſired; yet his charity herein is rather to be commended, then his ſentence in all thoſe to be embraced. For how theſe words of <hi>David (Be not merciful unto them who offend of malicious wickedneſs</hi>) ſhould be reducible to the form of a Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, is not ſo eaſily apprehended: Nor that St <hi>Paul,</hi> when he wiſhed, <hi>I would that they which trouble you were cut off;</hi> meant only with the ſword of excommunication, is not ſo eaſily believed, as ſome would have it. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience in our own ſufferings, is Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:171867:46"/> but when God ſuffers, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious. God ſuffers when his Truth is perſecuted and martyred: when therefore wicked men ſhall meerly ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of fained ſcrupuloſity, as doth the Beaſt of the Reeds; or elſe out of envie, as doth the Bulls, or out of ignorance, as do Calves of the people; or elſe out of ambition, as do the men that delight in miſchief; when I ſay, wicked men upon no other ground but ſuch as theſe, ſhall with bloody brains invent, as did the Beaſts of the Reeds, and with bloody conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences allow; and with a bloody Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion defend, as did the multitude of the Bulls, and with bloody affections advance, as did the Calves of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and with bloody hands execute, as did the men that delight in miſchief, ſuch ſacrilegious and bloody practiſes as theſe; then it is time for us to ſay, <hi>Rebuke, O Lord,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:171867:46"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
